Guide to the Social Ethics Pamphlet Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Topical Files, Series II
  - E-Q
    - International Organization, 1941-1958 (Box 110, Folder 16)
      Corporate Bodies:Churchpeace Union,: New York, NY; Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America: New York, NY; Mount Holyoke Institute on the United Nations:South Hadley, MA
      Comments: contains information about the founding of the United Nations and some of the controversy surrounding it
    - International Organization, 1954 (Box 110, Folder 16)
      Corporate Bodies:Committee for Economic Development: New York, NY; North Atlantic Treaty Organization: Paris, France; United States--Department of State
      Comments: contains papers and pamphlets about the founding and activities of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization
    - International Relations, 1949-1950 (Box 110, Folder 5)
      Subject Headings: Economic policy; International relations; War relief
      Corporate Bodies:Chancellor of the Exchequer: London, England; Netherlands--Government of
      Comments: contains pamphlets about the American economic plan for the reconstruction of Europe after the war
    - International Relations, 1951-1954 (Box 111, Folder 1)
      Subject Headings: International relations--China
      Corporate Bodies:Catholic Association for International Peace: Washington, DC; Harvard Business Review: Cambridge, MA; United States--Department of State
      Comments: contains papers on American policy toward China and the debate about recognition of China by the United Nations
    - International Relations, 1950-1953 (Box 111, Folder 2)
      Subject Headings: International relief
      Corporate Bodies:CIO,Washington,DC; Connecticut Conference of Churches--International Relations Commission; United States--Department of State
      Comments: contains materials on the Point Four Program of technical assistance to the "Third World" by the United States immediately following World War II
    - International Relations, 1948-1952 (Box 111, Folder 3)
      Corporate Bodies:Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America; United Nations: New York,NY; United States--Department of State
      Comments: contains papers on the proposal and passage of the United Nations Charter, Genocide Convention and Covenant of Human Rights
    - International Relations, 1941 (Box 111, Folder 4)
      Subject Headings:Church and social problems; International relations; Religion and culture; WorldWar, 1939-1945
      Corporate Bodies:Church League for Industrial Democracy; Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America,: New York, NY
      Comments: contains papers about the Malvern Declaration--a document issued by an Anglican conference in England which critiques the social and economic order of Europe as a reason for the War
    - Israel-Arab Conflicts, 1949, n.d. (Box 118, Folder 5)
      Subject Headings: Israel-Arab conflicts; Palestine
      Corporate Bodies:American Zionist Council: New york, NY
      Comments: contains papers about the issue of the division of Jerusalem which was considered by the United Nations in 1949
    - Israel-Arab Conflicts, 1947-1967 (Box 118, Folder 6)
      Subject Headings: Israel-Arab conflicts; New Haven; Palestine
      Corporate Bodies:New Haven Committee on the Middle East Crisis: New Haven, CT; United Nations: New York, NY
      Comments: contains papers and pamphlets on conflicts over Palestine and the Arab refugee crisis of 1948
    - Israel-Arab Conflicts, 1947-1956 (Box 118, Folder 7)
      Subject Headings:International relations; Israel; Palestine
      Corporate Bodies:American League for a Free Palestine: New York, NY; Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO): Washington, DC; Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America: New York, NY
      Comments: contains miscellaneous papers and pamphlets on the formation of the state of Israel and the United Nations policies toward Israel
    - Migrant Labor, 1951, n.d. (Box 111, Folder 6)
      Subject Headings: Migrant labor
      Comments: contains papers about Migrant Labor legislation, and programs run for migrant laborers by churches and businesses
    - Nativism, 1950, n.d. (Box 119, Folder 1)
      Subject Headings: Antisemitism; Nativism; Race relations; Religion and culture
      Corporate Bodies:American Jewish Committee: New York, NY
      Comments: contains copies of the series "Timely Biographies," which profiled leaders of nativist, antisemitic, fascist and racist organizations in the United States
    - Nativism, 1951, n.d. (Box 119, Folder 2)
      Corporate Bodies:Christian Nationalist Crusade: Los Angeles, CA
      Comments: contains papers and pamphlets issued by the Crusade: a nativist, antisemitic "Christian" movement led by Gerald L.K. Smith; for related materials see folders 119-3 & 4
    - Nativism, 1942-1948 (Box 119, Folder 3)
      Subject Headings: Nativism; Religion and culture
      Corporate Bodies: Cleveland Plain Dealer: Cleveland, OH; Colliers; PM Daily
      Comments: contains newsclippings critical of Gerald L. K. Smith and his movement; clippings are also contained about an 'uprising' of Ohio farmers in which Federal offices were vandalized and burned; for related materials see files 119-2& 4
    - Nativism, 1944-1950 (Box 119, Folder 4)
      Corporate Bodies: Christian Nationalist Crusade: Los Angeles, CA
      Comments: contains issues of the magazine "The Cross and The Flag," published by Gerald L.K. Smith; for related material see files 119-2 & 3
    - Nativism, 1944-1951 (Box 119, Folder 5)
      Subject Headings: Anti-Catholicism; Antisemitism; Labor movement; Nativism; Race relations; Religion and culture
      Corporate Bodies:Bible News Flashes: Minneapolis: MN; Defender Publishers: Wichita, KA; Militant Truth: Dayton, TN; Protestant News Service and Telegraphic Agency,Inc.: Washington, DC; Religious Liberty Association: Washington, DC
      Comments: contains papers issued by various organizations which sought to protect the "AmericanChristian" way of life
    - Nativism, 1954-1961 (Box 119, Folder 6)
      Subject Headings: Anti-communism; Antisemitism; Nativism; Racerelations; Religion and culture; United States--politics andgovernment
      Corporate Bodies: CommonSense: Union, NJ
      Comments: contains issuesof the newspaper: Common Sense a nativist anti-communist publication
    - Peace Movements, 1941-1951 (Box 111, Folder 7)
      Subject Headings: International relations; Peace movements; Nuclear disarmament; World War,1939-1945
      Corporate Bodies: Catholic Association for International Peace; Committee for Peaceful Alternatives: New York, NY; Connecticut Peace Council; Promoting Enduring Peace:West Haven, CT; Wesleyan Peace Fellowship
      Comments: contains papers issued by organizations seeking peace during World War II, and promoting nuclear disarmament during the early years of the Cold War
    - Poverty, 1965-1968 (Box 111, Folder 8)
      Subject Headings: Church and social problems; New Haven; Poverty
      Corporate Bodies:Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America
      Comments: contains papers about the problem of poverty nationally and in New Haven
    - Propaganda, 1948-1949 (Box 120, Folder 1)
      Subject Headings: Communism; Propaganda--communist
      Corporate Bodies:Information Bureau of the Cummunist and Worker's Parties
      Comments: contains issues of the communist newspaper "For A Lasting Peace, for a People's Democracy"which was published in Belgrade
    - Propaganda, 1950 (Box 120, Folder 10)
      Subject Headings: Propaganda--conservative
      Corporate Bodies:Ross Roy,Inc.: Detroit, MI
      Comments: contains pamphlets issued in the series "Land of the Free," a cartoon series favorably comparing capitalism to socialism; also contained is an analysis of the series prepared for the Michigan Council of Churches
    - Propaganda, 1939-1942 (Box 120, Folder 11)
      Subject Headings: Propaganda
      Corporate Bodies:Survey Graphic: Stroudsburg, PA
      Comments: contains issues of the magazine "Survey Graphic," which analyzes aspects of propaganda
    - Propaganda, 1949-1950 (Box 120, Folder 2)
      Subject Headings: Propaganda--communist; Soviet Union
      Corporate Bodies: Trud: Moscow,USSR
      Comments: contains issues of the communist magazine "New Times" published in Moscow
    - Propaganda (Box 120, Folder 4)
      Subject Headings: Propaganda--conservative; Communism; Subversive activities
      Corporate Bodies:American Anti-Communist League: St. Louis, MO; Liberty and Property: San Francisco, CA
      Comments: contains papers issued by several ultra-conservative groups
    - Propaganda, 1949, n.d. (Box 120, Folder 5, 6)
      Subject Headings: Czechoslovakia; Propaganda--communist
      Corporate Bodies:Czechoslovak Life: Prague, Czechoslovakia; Czechoslovak Union of Youth; Czechoslovakia Ministry of Information: Prague,; Czechoslovakia
      Comments: contains magazines about variuos aspects of life in Czechoslovakia and official publications of the government
    - Propaganda, 1949 (Box 120, Folder 7)
      Subject Headings: Poland; Propaganda--communist
      Corporate Bodies:Polish Research and Information Service: New York, NY
      Comments: contains issue of magazine "Poland of Today"
    - Propaganda, 1948 (Box 120, Folder 8)
      Subject Headings: German (East); Propaganda--communist
      Comments: contains 2 calendars profiling communist leaders and ideas
    - Propaganda, 1961 (Box 120, Folder 9)
      Subject Headings: Korea (North); Propaganda--communist
      Corporate Bodies:People's Korea: Tokyo, Japan
      Comments: contains one issue of the pro-communist newspaper "The People's Korea"
    - Propaganda, 1950-1956 (Box 129, Folder 3)
      Subject Headings: Propaganda--American
      Corporate Bodies:United States Advisory Committee on Information: Washington, DC; Information and Educational Exchange Program, State Department, United States Government:Washingon, DC; National Committee For an Adequate Overseas U.S. Information Program: Washington, DC
      Comments: contains pamphlets issued by the United States government
  - R-V
    - Race Relations, 1943-1951 (Box 121, Folder 1)
      Subject Headings: Education; Race relations
      Corporate Bodies:Atlanta University System: Atlanta, GA; National Broadcasting Company: New York, NY
      Comments: contains papers and pamphlets about equality in education and historically Black Colleges
    - Race Relations, 1941-1942 (Box 121, Folder 2)
      Subject Headings: Labor movement; Race relations
      Corporate Bodies:Opportunity, Journal of Negro Life
      Comments: contains papers about issues of race relations in labor and industry; also contained is a collection of articles from the magazine "Opportunity"
    - Race Relations, 1930-1946 (Box 121, Folder 3)
      Subject Headings: Lynching; Race relations
      Corporate Bodies:Association of Southern Women for the Prevention of Lynching: Atlanta, GA; Commission on Interracial Cooperation: Atlanta, GA; National association for the Advancement of Colored People: New York, NY; Southern Commission on the Study of Lynching: Atlanta, GA
      Comments: contains papers and pamphlets issued by organizations working against lynching, through social and legislative means
    - Race Relations, 1942, n.d. (Box 121, Folder 4)
      Subject Headings: African Americans; Labor movement; Lynching; Race relations
      Comments: contains newsclippings about race relations that were a part scrapbook kept by Dean Pope, includes index
    - Race Relations, 1946 (Box 121, Folder 5)
      Subject Headings: Church work with students; Education; Race Relations; Religion and culture
      Corporate Bodies: University Christian Mission, University of Oklahoma: Norman, Oklahoma
      Comments: contains papers on the controversy surrounding the cancellation of Religious emphasis week at the university because an African-American participant was barred from the program due to the segregation laws governing the university
    - Race Relations, 1947-1967 (Box 121, Folder 6)
      Subject Headings: Race relations; Religion and culture
      Corporate Bodies: Department of Social Education and Social Action, the United Christian Missionary Society: Indianapolis, IN; Race Relations Department of the American Missionary Association: New York, NY; Student Interracial Ministry: New York, NY
      Comments: contains miscellaneous papers and pamphlets issued by religious organizations on aspects of race relations
    - Race Relations, 1930-1943 (Box 121, Folder 7)
      Subject Headings: African Americans; Race relations
      Corporate Bodies:Community Relations Service: New York, NY; New York Public Library: New York, NY
      Comments: contains miscellaneous papers on race relations; also contained is a bibliography from the Schomberg Collection of works by and about African-Americans
    - Race Relations, 1958, n.d. (Box 121, Folder 8)
      Subject Headings: Race relations; Nativism; Subversive activities
      Corporate Bodies:American Nationalist: Inglewood, CA; Crusader Publishing Company: Childersburg AL; Headline: And Whats Behind Them: New Fairfield, CT; National Putnam Letters Committee
      Comments: contains papers and pamphlets issued by nativist and racist organizations
    - Religion and Culture, 1942, 1950 (Box 123, Folder 2)
      Subject Headings: Anglo-Israelism; Religion and culture
      Corporate Bodies: Destiny Publishers: Haverhill, MA; Kingdom Digest: Fort Worth, TX
      Comments: contains pamphlets issued by organizations espousing Anglo-Israelism: a belief that the United States and The United Kingdom are the lost tribes of Israel and Judah and heirs to the Israelite destiny
    - Religion and Culture (Box 123, Folder 8)
      Subject Headings: Religion and culture
      Corporate Bodies: American School of Christian Democracy: Kansas City, KA; Redemptorist Fathers: Ligouri, MO; Tolerance Press: Brooklyn, NY; Tract Club of America: Chicago, IL
      Comments: contains miscellaneous pamphlets about various aspects of religion and culture in the United States
    - Religion and Culture, 1951-1952 (Box 123, Folder 1)
      Subject Headings: Anti-Catholicism; Evangelicalism; Religion and culture
      Corporate Bodies: American Council of Christian Churches
      Comments: contains papers by and about the Council: a controversial fundamentalist movement headed by Carl McIntire (a deposed Presbyterian minister) critical of national and inetrnational ecumenical organizations; includes a report prepared for the Presbyterian Church U.S.A. about the organization
    - Religion and Culture, 1949-1950 (Box 123, Folder 3)
      Subject Headings: Ecumenical movement; Religion and culture; Subversive activities
      Corporate Bodies: Committee for Constitutional Government: New York, NY; Federal Council of churches of Christ in America: New York, NY; Friend's of Democracy's Battle: New York, NY
      Comments: contains materials about the attack on the Federal Council of Churches, labeling it as socialist and subversive, by John Flynn and the Committee for Constitutional Government; with rebuttals by the Council and commentary on Flynn and his organization
    - Religion and Culture, 1956-1961 (Box 123, Folder 4)
      Corporate Bodies: Christian Herald: New York, NY; National Council of Churches of Christ in America: New York, NY
      Comments: contains materials about attacks on the National Council of Churches as being a subversive, socialist organization
    - Religion and Culture, 1955 (Box 123, Folder 5)
      Corporate Bodies: National Council of Churches of Christ in America: New York, NY
      Comments: contains papers and pamphlets about the controversy surrounding the work of Norman Vincent Peale and the "prosperity gospel"; included is an article with commentary by Dean Pope
    - Religion and Culture, 1952, n.d. (Box 123, Folder 6)
      Subject Headings: Communism; Religion and culture
      Corporate Bodies:World Council of Churches: Geneva, Switzerland
      Comments: contains miscellaneous papers about the situation of the churches in East Germany
    - Religion and Culture, 1954 (Box 123, Folder 7)
      Corporate Bodies: Religious Research Fellowship: New York, NY
      Comments: contains papers about a conference concerned with the demographic and geographic requirements for the establishment of a successful mainline Protestant church
    - Religious Freedom, 1952 (Box 111, Folder 10)
      Subject Headings: North Carolina--church history; Religious Freedom
      Corporate Bodies: Chapel Hill Presbyterian Church: Chapel Hill, NC; Orange Presbytery: NC
      Comments: contains papers about the case of Charles Jones, a Presbyterian minister whom the Presbytery sought to remove from his church because of his teachings and views on church order
    - Religious Freedom, 1949, n.d. (Box 111, Folder 11)
      Subject Headings: New York--church history; Religious Freedom
      Comments: contains papers about the case of the removal of an Episcopal priest from his church by the diocese because of his political activities and association with progressive organizations
    - Social Legislation, 1943-1951 (Box 122, Folder 1)
      Subject Headings: Economic policy; Medical care; Social legislation
      Corporate Bodies: American Medical Association: Chicago, IL
      Comments: contains papers and pamphlets issued by the AMA which opposed national health care legislation which was considered between 1942 and 1953
    - Social Legislation, 1944 (Box 122, Folder 10)
      Subject Headings: Economic policy; Medical care; Public opinion; Social legislation
      Corporate Bodies: National Opinion Research Center: Denver, CO
      Comments: contains a nationwide survey done by the Center about national health care
    - Social Legislation, 1946 (Box 122, Folder 11)
      Corporate Bodies: School of Public Health, University of Michigan: Ann Arbor, MI
      Comments: contains a monthly journal issued by the school on issues and events related to the national health care debate
    - Social Legislation, 1946-1952 (Box 122, Folder 2)
      Corporate Bodies: Committee for the Nation's Health: New York, NY
      Comments: contains papers and pamphlets issued by the Committee supporting the national health care legislation proposed from 1942 thru 1953
    - Social Legislation, 1948 (Box 122, Folder 3)
      Corporate Bodies: Federal Security Agency: Washington, DC
      Comments: contains copy and commentary on the "Ewing Report" prepared by the government during the national health care debate of 1942-1953
    - Social Legislation, 1946-1948 (Box 122, Folder 4)
      Corporate Bodies: National Physician's Committee
      Comments: contains papers and pamphlets issued by the Committee, an AMA public relations agency, critical of the proposed national health care legislation of 1942-1953
    - Social Legislation, 1945 (Box 122, Folder 5)
      Corporate Bodies: Physicians Forum: New York, NY
      Comments: contains papers from the Forum, a group of physicians supporting the national health care legislation of 1942-1953
    - Social Legislation, 1947-1948 (Box 122, Folder 6)
      Comments: contains papers about the national health care proposals which were put before congress in 1947
    - Social Legislation, 1948-1952 (Box 122, Folder 7)
      Corporate Bodies: The Freeman: New York, NY; Insurance Economics Society of America: Chicago, IL
      Comments: contains miscellaneous papers and pamphlets critical of the national health care proposals of 1942-1953
    - Social Legislation, 1947-1948 (Box 122, Folder 8)
      Corporate Bodies: American Federationist; The Churchman: New York, NY
      Comments: contains miscellaneous papers and pamphlets supporting the proposed national health legislation of 1942-1953
    - Social Legislation, 1949-1950, n.d. (Box 122, Folder 9)
      Subject Headings: Economic policy; Medical care; Social legislation; Yale University
      Corporate Bodies: Atlantic Monthly: New York, NY; Committee on Research and Medical Economics: New York, NY; Modern Industry: New York, NY; Yale University: New Haven CT
      Comments: contains miscellaneous papers outlining the debate over national health care proposals; included are materials from a health care forum jointly sponsored by the Divinity, Law and Medical schools of Yale University
    - Southern States, 1942-1945 (Box 111, Folder 9)
      Subject Headings: Civil Rights; Southern states; United States--politics and government
      Corporate Bodies: National Committee to Abolish the Poll Tax: Washington, DC; Parents and Wives of Fighting Americans, Inc.: New York, NY; Southern Conference for Human Welfare: Nashville, TN; Workers Defense League: New York, NY
      Comments: contains papers and pamphlets issued by organizations challenging the poll tax statutes in 7 Southern states
    - Subversive Activities, 1953-1955 (Box 111, Folder 12)
      Subject Headings: Civil rights; Subversive Activities; United States--politics and government
      Corporate Bodies: I.F.Stone's Weekly: Washington, DC
      Comments: contains three issues of the newsletter which commented on the civil liberties issues raised by the activities of the congressional Un-American Activities Committee
    - Subversive Activities, 1953-1954 (Box 111, Folder 13)
      Subject Headings: Civil rights; Joseph McCarthy; Subversive activities; United states--politics and government
      Corporate Bodies: The New Republic: New York, NY; The Progrssive: Madison, WI
      Comments: contains issues of the New Republic and the Progressive which profile the activities of Senator Joseph McCarthy and their assault on civil liberties
    - Subversive Activities, 1938-1945 (Box 111, Folder 14)
      Subject Headings: Labor movement; Race relations; Religion and culture; Subversive activities
      Corporate Bodies: Jewish Theological Seminary of America: New York, NY; People's Institute of Applied Religion: Detroit, MI; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A., Synod of Michigan
      Comments: contains materials on the activities of Claude Williams and the Institute of Applied Religion (a progressive organization which worked with labor and race issues); also contains papers about the heresy trial in which Williams was defrocked by the Synod of Michigan for subversive activities
    - United States--Politics and Government, 1954 (Box 111, Folder 15)
      Subject Headings: Civil Rights; International relations; United States--politics and government
      Corporate Bodies: Christian Action: New York, NY; Church Peace Union: New York, NY; Committee for the Defense of the Constiuttion: New York, NY
      Comments: contains papers about the Bricker Amendment to the constitution which was proposed in 1953, and would have made it virtually impossible for the president to sign a treaty which was binding on the internal affairs of the United States (i.e., United Nations Human Rights Declaration)
    - United States--Politics and Government, 1944-1964 (Box 111, Folder 15a)
      Subject Headings: United States--politics and government
      Corporate Bodies: Citizens for Eisenhower-Nixon: New York, NY; Democratic National Committee: Washington, DC; Liberty Lobby: Washington, DC; Republican National Committee: New York, NY
      Comments: contains miscellaneous political and campaign literature
    - United States--Social Conditions-1933-1945 (Box 124, Folder 3)
      Subject Headings: Conservatism--literature; Economic policy; United States-politics and governement; United States--Social Conditions-1933-1945
      Corporate Bodies: Coast Federal Savings: Los Angeles, CA; Jefferson-Hamilton Coalition: Tulsa, OK
      Comments: contains pamphlets issued by economically conservative organizations about the post-war economic policy of the United States